Preliminary Guide to the Roma Stewart Goodwin Blackburn Papers, 1942-1985 and undated
Roma Stewart Goodwin Blackburn papers 1942-1985 and undated
Blackburn, Roma Stewart Goodwin
1.2 Linear Feet 564 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, some of the additions to this collection are not immediately accessible, because they require further processing before use.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the Rare Book, Manuscript, and Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Roma Steward Goodwin Blackburn Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1982-1984, 2001, and 2012.
Biographical Note
Lawyer, poet, and writer originally from Prince Edward Island, Canada.
Collection Overview
Primarily correspondence between Roma Blackburn and literary personages, including former students of her husband, William Maxwell Blackburn, professor at Duke University. Also includes poem by Rose Styron, clippings about the poet Elizabeth Bishop, and a program from Bishop's memorial service. One volume, Heart and Home: A Memoir, was written by Mrs. Blackburn. Correspondence includes: letters and postcards from Elizabeth Bishop discussing travels, intellectual life, and literary interests; letters from William Styron discussing fund-raising in memory of Professor William Blackburn for the Duke University Capital Campaign for the Arts and Sciences; letters from Alice Methfessel, close friend of Elizabeth Bishop; and letters from Professor Blackburn's former students Sean Devereaux, Guy Davenport, and Josephine Humphreys Hutcheson. (1964-1984) (46 items) (.2 linear feet)
This addition (218 items, 1942-1985) includes letters to Blackburn from Reynolds Price and Wallace Fowlie and others regarding invitations, travel plans, news, and condolences; material related to the William Blackburn Fund; correspondence from Blackburn's summers in Magog; a story by Max Steele; 23 manuscript pages of Blackburn's autobiography; copies of tributes to William Blackburn from William Styron and Max Steele as well as statistics on the number of students he taught; and photographs (61 black-and-white prints, 4 color prints, 1 color slide, and 2 black-and-white negatives) of Tennessee Williams, Fred Chappell, William Styron, Sean Devereaux, Wallace Fowlie, and William Blackburn as well as other family members. An unidentified audio tape is included. (.6 linear feet) (acc#01-0036)
Addition (2012-0038) (0.4 lin. ft., 300 items) includes personal correspondence to Roma Blackburn from family members and others, clippings and photographs of William Blackburn, and a recording of William Styron reading from Lie Down in Darkness. Also included are writings and notes by William Blackburn mostly relating to his W.B. Yeats research.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Bishop, Elizabeth, 1911-1979
Blackburn, William (William Maxwell), 1899-1972
Chappell, Fred, 1936-
Fowlie, Wallace, 1908-
Price, Reynolds, 1933-
Steele, Max, 1922-
Styron, Rose
Styron, William, 1925-
Methfessel, Alice
Devereaux, Sean
Humphreys, Josephine
Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983
Yeats, W. B. (William Butler), 1865-1939
Duke University. Capital Campaign for the Arts and Sciences
Duke University -- Faculty
College teaching -- United States
Authors, American -- 20th century -- Correspondence
Women poets -- United States -- Biography
Women poets -- Correspondence
American poetry -- Women authors
United States -- Intellectual life -- 20th century
Black-and-white photographs
Color photographs
Color slide
Black-and-white negatives
Audiocassette tape
Contents of Collection
- Accession March 1, 1982
  - Correspondence, 1978-1984 (Box 1)
    "Brenley," Magog, Canada, and Durham, NC
- Accession April 30, 1984
  - Addresses and writings, ca. 1967 (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1978-1983
  - Heart and Home: A Memoir
- Accession 2001-0036
  - Unidentified audio cassette tape (Box 1)
  - Photographs, (2 folders)
    Includes 61 black and white photos, 5 color photos, 1 color slide, 2 black and white negatives. Photo subjects include Tennessee Williams, Fred Chappell, William Styron, Sean Devereaux, Wallace Fowlie, and William Blackburn (head shots and candid shots), and other unidentified authors and family members.
  - Letters received, 1973-1981, (1 folder)
    Includes regular correspondence and catching up letters, invitations and travel plans, academic news, and condolence letters.
  - Letters received, 1973-1981, (3 folders) (Box 2)
  - Letters received, 1973-1985, (2 folders)
    Includes correspondence from Roma Blackburn's summers in Magog, a memorial article about William Blackburn, and information about a biography being written. Frequent correspondents include Reynolds Price and Wallace Fowlie.
  - Materials on the Blackburn Campaign (for scholarships) 1962-1984
  - Roma Blackburn's autobiography, p. 196-219
  - Testimonials and teaching - William Blackburn
  - Letters from Wallace Fowlie to Roma Blackburn, 1973-1981
  - Story by Max Steele, mailed to Roma Blackburn 1980
  - Newspaper and magazine articles, 1972, 1983-1985
- Accession (2012-0038), (1 box)
  Addition (2012-0038) (0.4 lin. ft., 300 items) includes personal correspondence to Roma Blackburn from family members and others, clippings and photographs of William Blackburn, and a recording of William Styron reading from Lie Down in Darkness. Also included are writings and notes by William Blackburn mostly relating to his W.B. Yeats research.
  This accession requires further processing before use.
  - Correspondence
    - Personal, 1962-1977 (Box 3)
    - Personal, 1968-1989 (Box 3)
    - Letters to Roma Blackburn from Blackburn family, 1972-1978 (Box 3)
  - Photographs (Box 3)
  - Recordings
    - William Styron reading Lie Down in Darkness, (1 LP) (Box 3)
  - William Blackburn
    - Articles and clippings about William Blackburn (Box 3)
    - Obituary notices (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous writings and notes (Box 3)
    - Yeats research notes, drafts, and correspondence, (2 folders) (Box 3)